In 2008, Cyclone Nargis devastated Myanmar.
في عام 2008 ، دمر إعصار نرجس ميانمار.
Millions of people were in severe need of help.
ملايين الناس كان في حاجة ماسة للمساعدة.
The U.N. wanted to rush people and supplies to the area.
أرادت الأمم المتحدة الإسراع بتقديم المساعدات وإرسال الناس.
But there were no maps, no maps of roads,
لكن لم تكن هناك خرائط للطرق،
no maps showing hospitals, no way for help to reach the cyclone victims.
لا توجد خرائط للمستشفيات، لا سبيل لوصول المساعدة لضحايا الإعصار
When we look at a map of Los Angeles or London,
عندما نرى خارطة لوس أنجلوس، أو لندن
it is hard to believe
من الصعب تصديق
that as of 2005, only 15 percent of the world
أن حتى العام 2005 فقط 15 في المائة من العالم
was mapped to a geo-codable level of detail.
تم تخطيطه إلى مستوى من التفاصيل قابلة للترميز الجغرافي
The U.N. ran headfirst into a problem
وقعت الأمم المتحدة في المشكلة
that the majority of the world's populous faces:
التي يواجهها غالبية سكان العالم:
not having detailed maps.
عدم وجود خرائط تفصيلية.
But help was coming.
لكن المساعدات كانت قادمة.
At Google, 40 volunteers
في قوقل، 40 متطوعاً
used a new software
أستخدموا برمجيات جديدة
to map 120,000 kilometers of roads,
لرسم خارطة 120 ألف كيلومتراً من الطرق،
3,000 hospitals, logistics and relief points.
3 ألف مستشفى، لوجستيات و نقاط إغاثة.
And it took them four days.
وأستغرق الأمر منهم 4 أيام.
The new software they used? Google Mapmaker.
البرنامج الجديد الذي أستخدموه؟ صانع الخرائط لقوقل.
Google Mapmaker is a technology that empowers each of us
صانع خرائط قوقل هو تكنلوجيا تعزز أي واحد منّا
to map what we know locally.
لرسم خارطة ما يعرفه محلياً.
People have used this software
أستخدم الناس هذا البرنامج
to map everything from roads to rivers,
لرسم خارطة لأي شئ من الطرق الى الأنهار،
from schools to local businesses,
من المدارس الى الشركات المحلية،
and video stores to the corner store.
ومتاجر الفيديو الى المتاجر في النواصي.
Maps matter.
الخرائط مهمة.
Nobel Prize nominee Hernando De Soto
المرشح لنيل جائزة نوبل هيرناندو دي سوتو
recognized that the key to economic liftoff
أقرّ بأن مفتاح نهضة الإقتصاد
for most developing countries
لمعظم الدول النامية
is to tap the vast amounts of uncapitalized land.
هو إستغلال المساحات الشاسعة للأراضي غير المستغلة.
For example, a trillion dollars
على سبيل المثال، تريليون دولار
of real estate remains uncapitalized in India alone.
للعقارات لم تستغل في الهند وحدها.
In the last year alone,
في السنة الماضية فقط،
thousands of users in 170 countries
آلالاف المستخدمين في 170 دولة
have mapped millions of pieces of information,
خططوا ملايين القطع من المعلومات،
and created a map of a level of detail never thought viable.
وصنعوا خارطة على مستوى من التفصيل لم يخطر ببال أحد.
And this was made possible by
وهذا أصبح ممكناً بواسطة
the power of passionate users everywhere.
قوة المستخدمين الطامحين في كل مكان.
Let's look at some of the maps
لنلقي نظرة على بعض الخرط
being created by users right now.
التي يتم صنعها بواسطة المستخدمين الآن.
So, as we speak, people are mapping the world
إذاً، بينما نتحدث يخطط الناس العالم
in these 170 countries.
في هذه ال 170 دولة.
You can see Bridget in Africa who just mapped a road in Senegal.
يمكنكم رؤية بريدجيت في أفريقيا الذي قام للتو تم تخطيط طريق في السنغال.
And, closer to home, Chalua, an N.G. road in Bangalore.
و، قريباً من الوطن، تشالوا، طريق في بانغالور.
This is the result of computational geometry,
هذه نتيجة الرسم الهندسي،
gesture recognition, and machine learning.
التعرف على الإشارات، وتدريب الحواسيب.
This is a victory of thousands of users,
هذا إنتصار لآلاف المستخدمين،
in hundreds of cities,
في مئات من المدن،
one user, one edit at a time.
مستخدم واحد، يقوم بالتحرير مرة في كل وقت.
This is an invitation to the 70 percent
هذه دعوة للسبعين في المائة
of our unmapped planet.
من كوكبنا غير المرسومة خرئطه.
Welcome to the new world.
مرحباً بكم في العالم الجديد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)